United States Fisheries Commission Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
United States Fisheries Commission Archives
1871-1907
IZAR.000985
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
10
U.S. Fish Commission archives generated during A.E. Verrill's involvement with the Commission from 1871-1887.
U.S. Fish Commission
Biographical Sketch
The United States Fisheries Commission (USFC) was a government program which began in 1871 to investigate potential fisheries and marine faunal areas. Addison Verrill was involved as head scientist from 1871 to 1887 and much of his research is based on this material. Much of the Division of Invertebrate Zoology is made up of these collections and a majority are lots that were split between the Smithsonian's National Museum of Natural History (USNM) and the Yale Peobody Museum (YPM). Much of thes archives were generated by assistants to Verrill.
Description of the Material
These archives include original station notebooks and distribution sheets. The distribution sheets contain information on how the specimen lots were divided up between the USNM and YPM.
USA; Atlantic Ocean; Gulf of Maine; Gulf of Mexico; Caribbean Sea; Station notebooks; Maps; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Station Notebooks, 1871-1887; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  These are the original station notebooks compiled by an observer while on board the vessels.
  - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station notebooks for the USFC Stmr. Bluelight., 1873-1875; 000988
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 6. Station data and list of species collected from 03 Aug to 14 Aug., 03 Aug 1873 - 14 Aug 1873; 001049
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1874 Dredging Book No. 1. Shore lists and miscellaneous species lists., 07 Jul 1874 - 09 Jul 1874; 001052
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1874 Dredging Book No. 3. Haul data and species lists., 08 Aug 1874 - 24 Aug 1874; 001525
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations Bluelight Hauls 48-66.., 11 Aug 1873 - 03 Sep 1873; 001060
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for USFC Sta. 486-536., 11 Aug 1874 - 24 Aug 1874; 001062
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 1. Station data and list of species collected from 12 Jul to 14 Jul., 12 Jul 1873 - 14 Jul 1873; 001044
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1875 Dredging Book No. 1. Haul's 1-19, species lists., 12 Jul 1875 - 15 Jul 1875; 001055
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for USFC Sta. 601-630 (Copied from Clark's Notes) and USFC Sta. 733 - 769. Recorded by S.F. Clark and A. Hyatt.., 12 Jul 1875 - 20 Sep 1875; 001065
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Original station data for USFC Sta's. 682-730, recorded aboard the USFC Stmr. Bluelught by S.F. Clark., 13 Aug 1875 - 03 Sep 1875; 000989
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 2. Station data and list of species collected from 14 Jul to 16 Jul., 14 Jul 1873 - 16 Jul 1873; 001045
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 3. Station data and list of species collected from 16 Jul to 21 Jul., 16 Jul 1873 - 21 Jul 1873; 001046
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1875 Dredging Book No. 3. Haul's 86-122, species lists., 17 Aug 1875 - 02 Sep 1875; 001057
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Dredging Papers No. 8 and Shore Lists. Station data and list of species collected from 20 Aug 1873 as well as from shore localities., 001051
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for Bluelight HaULS 1-48., 20 Jul 1873 - 03 Sep 1873; 001059
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1875 Dredging Book No. 2. Haul's 20-85, species lists., 20 Jul 1875 - 16 Aug 1875; 001056
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 4. Station data and list of species collected from 21 Jul to 29 Jul., 21 Jul 1873 - 29 Jul 1873; 001047
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for USFC Sta. 427-485.., 22 Jul 1874 - 11 Aug 1874; 001061
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1874 Dredging Book No. 4. Haul data and species lists., 24 Aug 1874 - 30 Aug 1874; 001054
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for USFC Sta. 542-580., 25 Aug 1874 - 03 Sep 1874; 001063
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Station Record Book. Original station data and observations for USFC Sta. 631-681. Recorded by S.F. Clark., 26 Jul 1875 - 13 Aug 1875; 001064
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Dredging Papers No. 7. Station data and list of species collected from 27 Aug to 30 Aug., 27 Aug 1873 - 30 Aug 1873; 001050
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. Casco Bay Dredging Papers No. 5. Station data and list of species collected from 29 Jul to 02 Aug., 29 Jul 1873 - 02 Aug 1873; 001048
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1874 Dredging Book No. 2. Haul data and species lists., Jul 1874 - Aug 1874; 001053
    - USFC Stmr. Bluelight. 1875 Dredging Book No. 4, species lists., Jul 1875 - Aug 1875; 001058
  - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station notebooks for the USFC Stmr. Speedwell., 1877-1879; 001066
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 1-58., 04 Aug 1877 - 25 Aug 1877; 001067
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 285-326., 06 Aug 1879 - 01 Sep 1879; 001074
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 227-370., 06 Sep 1879 - 19 Sep 1879; 001075
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 371-378., 19 Sep 1879 - 26 Sep 1879; 001076
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 103-128., 20 Sep 1877 - 17 Oct 1877; 001069
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 239-284., 21 Jul 1879 - 04 Aug 1879; 001073
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 129-175., 23 Jul 1878 - 27 Aug 1878; 001070
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 226-238., 23 Sep 1878 - 26 Sep 1878; 001072
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 176-225., 27 Aug 1878 - 21 Sep 1878; 001071
    - USFC Stmr. Speedwell. Station Record Book. Original station and observation records for USFC Sta. 59-102., 28 Aug 1877 - 15 Sep 1877; 001068
- Distribution Sheets, 1907; Series II
  These are the specimen distribution sheets compiled during an audit in 1907. It lists all lots and which institutions they were distributed to.
  - Annelida. Annelida distribution sheets., 1907; 001883
    - Annelida A-Cistenides. Annelida A-Cistenides distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001884
    - Annelida Clitellio-Lysippe. Annelida Clitellio-Lysippe distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001885
    - Annelida Maldane-Nicomache. Annelida Maldane-Nicomache distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001886
    - Annelida Ninoe-Pseudopotamilla. Annelida Ninoe-Pseudopotamilla distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001887
    - Annelida Rhodine-Steraspis. Annelida Rhodine-Steraspis distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001888
    - Annelida Sthenelais-Z. Annelida Sthenelais-Z distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001889
    - Annelida. Annelida distribution sheets. Rough copies., 1907; 001945
    - Oligochaeta & Acanthocephala. Oligochaeta & Acanthocephala distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001891
  - Cnidaria. Cnidaria distribution sheets., 1907; 001870
    - Actiniaria. Actiniaria distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001871
    - Alcyonaria. Alcyonaria distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001872
    - Alcyonaria. Alcyonaria distribution sheets. Rough copies., 1907; 001943
    - Alcyonaria. Alcyonaria distribution sheets. Rough copies., 1907; 001950
    - Hydrozoa A-N. Hydrozoa A-N distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001873
    - Hydrozoa O-Z. Hydrozoa O-Z distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001874
    - Madreporaria. Madreporaria distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001875
  - Crustacea. Crustacea distribution sheets., 1899-1907; 001711
    - Amphipoda. Amphipoda distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001876
    - Anomura. Anomura distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001905
    - Brachyura. Brachyura distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001906
    - Cirrepedia. Cirrepedia distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001877
    - Copepoda. Copepoda distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001878
    - Crustacea. Anomura distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001712
    - Crustacea. Amphipoda distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001713
    - Crustacea. Isopoda distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001714
    - Crustacea. "Macrura" = Caridea, Peneidea distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001715
    - Crustacea. Stomatopoda distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001716
    - Crustacea. Brachyura distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001717
    - Cumacea. Cumacea distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001879
    - Decapoda larvae, etc. Decapoda larvae, etc. distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001907
    - Isopoda. Isopoda distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001880
    - Macrura (1). Macrura (1) distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001908
    - Macrura (2). Macrura (2) distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001909
    - Macrura. Macrura distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001881
    - Ostracoda, Phyllopoda, etc. Ostracoda, Phyllopoda, etc. distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001890
    - Schizopoda. Schizopoda distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001882
    - Stomatopoda. Stomatopoda distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001910
  - Echinodermata. Echinodermata distribution sheets., 1899-1907; 001709
    - Asteroidea & Ophiuroidea. Asteroidea & Ophiuroidea distribution sheets. Rough copy., 1907; 001947
    - Asteroidea. Asteroidea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001911
    - Crinoidea. Crinoidea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001912
    - Echinodermata. Echinodermata distribution sheets. Not final copies though., 1899-1907; 001710
    - Echinodermata. Ophiuriodea distribution sheets. Not final copies., 1899-1907; 001718
    - Echinoidea. Echinoidea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001913
    - Holothuroidea. Holothuroidea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001914
    - Holothuroidea. Holothuroidea distribution sheets. Rough copy., 1907; 001949
    - Ophiuroidea. Ophiuroidea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001915
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous archives releated to distribution sheets., 1899; 001790
    - Ascidiacea. Ascidiacea distribution sheets. Rough copy., 1871-1907; 001946
    - Ascidiacea. Ascidiacea distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001916
    - Balonoglossus. Balonoglossus distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001917
    - Bryozoa. Bryozoa distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001918
    - Chaetognatha. Chaetognatha distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001919
    - Explanation. Explanation of distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001904
    - Foraminfera & Bottom Samples. Foraminfera & Bottom Samples distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001902
    - Fossils. Fossils distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001920
    - Insects. Insects distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001921
    - Limulus. Limulus distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001922
    - Miscellaneous. Rough copies of distrubution sheets, various phyla. Some with notes made by Verrill, Bush, etc., 1871-1907; 001941
    - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous distribution sheets., 1871-1907; 001954
    - Miscellaneous. Notes from K.J. Bush regarding corrections made on distribution sheets mostly involving mollusca., 1899; 001791
    - N.P. Scudder Collection. N.P. Scudder Collection distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001923
    - Nematoda. Nematoda distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001925
    - Priapulida. Priapulida distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001903
    - Stomach Contents. Stomach Contents distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001924
  - Mollusca. Mollusca distribution sheets., 1899-1907; 001707
    - Cephalopoda. Cephalopoda distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001927
    - Mollusca A. Mollusca A distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001928
    - Mollusca B. Mollusca B distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001929
    - Mollusca C (1). Mollusca C (1) distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001930
    - Mollusca C (2). Mollusca C (2) distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001931
    - Mollusca D-K. Mollusca D-K distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001932
    - Mollusca L. Mollusca L distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001933
    - Mollusca M. Mollusca M distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001934
    - Mollusca N. Mollusca N distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001935
    - Mollusca O-R. Mollusca O-R distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001936
    - Mollusca S. Mollusca S distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001937
    - Mollusca T. Mollusca T distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001938
    - Mollusca U-Z. Mollusca U-Z distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001939
    - Mollusca reserved for A.E Verrill. Mollusca reserved for A.E Verrill distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001940
    - Mollusca. Duplicate Mollusca distribution sheets., 1907; 001942
    - Mollusca. Mollusca distribution sheets. Rough copy., 1907; 001948
    - Mollusca. Distribution sheets of Mollusca (mostly Pleurotomella) with citations and description of species. Possibly used for a manuscript. Most of the handwritting is K.J. Bush., 1907; 001951
    - Mollusca. Distribution sheets of Mollusca (mostly Bela) with citations and description of species. Possibly used for a manuscript. Most of the handwritting is K.J. Bush., 1907; 001952
    - Mollusca. Distribution sheets of Mollusca with citations and description of species. Possibly used for a manuscript. Most of the handwritting is K.J. Bush., 1907; 001953
    - Mollusca. Mollusca distribution sheets. Found labeled as "Corrections listed Feb. 1899. This set used in Dividing.", 001708
    - Solenogastres, Misc. Mollusca. Solenogastres, Misc. Mollusca distribution sheets. Final copy., 1907; 001926
  - Nemertea. Nemertea distribution sheets., 1907; 001896
    - Nemertea. Nemertea distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001899
  - Platyhelminthes. Platyhelminthes distribution sheets., 1907; 001892
    - Bdellodea. Bdellodea distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001893
    - Planaria. Planaria distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001894
    - Trematoda & Cestoda. Trematoda & Cestoda distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001895
  - Porifera. Porifera distribution sheets., 1907; 001897
    - Porifera. Porifera distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001900
  - Pycnogonida. Pycnogonida distribution sheets., 1907; 001898
    - Pycnogonida. Pycnogonida distribution sheets. Final copies., 1907; 001901
    - Pycnogonida. Pycnogonida distribution sheets. Rough copies., 1907; 001944
- Verrill Retained Collections, 1873-1887; Series III
  Catalogs of specimens collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill.
  - Cnidaria. Catalogs of Cnidaria collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001018
    - Cnidaria. Hydrozoa collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001752
    - Cnidaria. Actiniaria collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001753
    - Cnidaria. Alcyonaria and Madreporaria collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001019
    - Cnidaria. Actiniaria collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001020
    - Cnidaria. Gorgonacea and Pennatulacea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001751
  - Crustacea. Catalogs of Crustacea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001040
    - Crustacea. List of Crustacea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001041
    - Crustacea. List of Crustacea sent to New Haven from Woods Hole, 1883., 001743
  - Echinodermata. Catalogs of Echinodermata collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001023
    - Echinodermata. Asteroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001754
    - Echinodermata. Holothuroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001756
    - Echinodermata. Echinoidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001757
    - Echinodermata. Ophiuroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1872-1887; 001758
    - Echinodermata. Holothuroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001024
    - Echinodermata. Asteroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001025
    - Echinodermata. Ophiuroidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001026
    - Echinodermata. Echinoidea collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001755
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous specimens collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001719
    - Miscellaneous. Lists of Crustacea, Porifera, Ascidiacea, Hydroida, Bryozoa, etc retained by Verrill.Found tied together., 1873-1887; 001720
  - Mollusca. Catalogs of Mollusca collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001027
    - Mollusca. Cephalopoda collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001028
    - Mollusca. A lis of the Cephalopoda collected by the USFC from 1873 to 1887 and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1896; 001205
  - Porifera. Catalogs of Porifera collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001021
    - Porifera. Porifera collected by the USFC and retained by A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001022
- Specimen Lists, 1871-1907; Series IV
  Miscellaneous lists of USFC specimens, either retained by the YPM or returned to the USNM.
  - Albatross Specimens. Lists of specimens collected by the Albatross., 1883-1887; 001721
    - Albatross Specimens. List of Mollusca dregded by Albatross in summer of 1884., 001722
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous USFC specimen lists., 1871-1907; 001955
    - Miscellaneous. A chart of various species vs. localities most likely to be used to check for the presence of the listed species in the listed loaclities. However, it appears to of not been used., 1871-1907; 001956
  - Mollusca. Lists of USFC Mollusca specimens., 1871-1907; 001030
    - Mollusca. List of Bivalvia specimens collected by the USFC., 1871-1907; 001031
    - Mollusca. List of Gastropoda specimens collected by the USFC., 1871-1907; 001032
    - Mollusca. A catalog of a collection of Mollusca, Brachiopoda, etc. for Sanderson Smith., 1873-1887; 001213
  - Returned Specimen Lists. Lists of USFC specimens returned to the USNM., 1871-1907; 001033
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 01 Apr 1895; 001733
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine invertebrates (non Mollusca) collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 01 Apr 1895; 001746
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 15 Dec 1898; 001735
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of USFC collections, Labrador collections and Blake collections of Crustacea, Cephalopoda, Echinodermata, Anthazoa, etc. sent to USNM ca. 1883-1884., 001035
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of specimens returned to USNM., 1885; 001036
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca made at Woods Hole, MA, Summer 1887 and collected by the USFC. Most sent to USNM, some sent to YPM., 001739
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 19 Mar 1896; 001736
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine invertebrates (non Mollusca) collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 19 Mar 1896; 001744
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 20 May 1895; 001738
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine invertebrates (non Mollusca) collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 20 May 1895; 001747
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 21 Dec 1894; 001737
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine Cnidaria, Echinodermata collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 21 Dec 1894; 001748
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine Crustacea collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 21 Dec 1894; 001749
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 22 Jun 1894; 001732
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine invertebrates (non Mollusca) collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 22 Jun 1894; 001750
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Crustacea sent to USNM by A.E. Verrill., 25 Mar 1898; 001034
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of marine invertebrates (non Mollusca) collected by the USFC and returned to the USNM by A.E. Verrill., 30 Jun 1896; 001745
    - Retuned Specimen Lists. List of Mollusca collected by the USFC and returned to USNM by Verrill., 30 Oct 1897; 001734
  - U.S. National Museum Register. Copies of USNM register., 1894-1899; 001729
    - U.S. National Museum Register. Catalog of Crustacea. USNM 7938-8740, 1883-1884; 001742
    - U.S. National Museum Register. Catalog of Sponges, Protozoans. USNM 1592-1730. Tunicata USNM 261-297., 1884; 001741
    - U.S. National Museum Register. Catalog of Radiata. USNM 16189-16312. Some specimens sent to Washington, some to the Peabody., 1887; 001740
    - U.S. National Museum Register. Copies of USNM register. All are of Mollusca. They include USNM 52219-52887, 73051-77637, 78000-78991., 1894-1899; 001730
    - U.S. National Museum Register. List of Mollusca, USNM 51200-52000. Sent to USNM in 1894., 001731